[Music]
drink two cups of water and you get a
surge of the adrenal hormone nor
adrenaline your bloodstream as if you
just smoked a few cigarettes or downed a
few cups of coffee which boost your
metabolic rate up to 30% within an hour
which when put to the test in randomized
control trials appear to accelerate
weight loss by 44% certainly making it
the safest simplest and cheapest way to
boost your metabolism now if you're on a
beta blocker drug this entire strategy
May Fail beta blockers are typically
prescribed for heart conditions or high
blood pressure and tend to end with the
uh letters LOL such as a tenolol natol
or propanolol sold do to Norman cor
guard or Inderal respectively so for
example if you give people the beta
blocker drug mol so just l pressure
before they chug their two cups of water
the metabolic boost is effectively
prevented this makes sense since the
beta that's being blocked in beta
blockers are the beta receptors
triggered by nor adrenaline otherwise
though the water should work but what's
the best kind of dose type temperature
and timing just a single cup may be
sufficient to rev up the nor adrenaline
nerves but additional benefit is see
them at two or more cups uh caution one
should never drink more than three cups
in an hour though since that starts to
exceed the amount of fluid your kidneys
can handle if you have a hard or kidney
failure your physician may not want you
drinking extra water at all but even
with healthy kidneys any more than three
cups of water an hour can start to
critically dilute the electrolytes in
your brain with uh potentially critical
consequences in uh how not to diet I
talk about the first patient I ever
killed in the hospital as an intern I
was a guy who drunk himself to death
with water he suffered from a
neurological condition that causes
pathological thirst knew enough to order
his liquids be restricted and to have
his sink shut off but didn't think to
turn off his toilet anyways does it have
to be plain straight water it shouldn't
seem to matter right I mean water is
water whether flavor it or sweeten in
some diet drink but it does matter when
trying to prevent fainting before blood
donations something like juice doesn't
work as well as plain water when trying
to uh keep people from getting dizzy
when they stand up or water works but
the same amount of water with salt added
doesn't what's going on we used to think
the trigger was stomach distension when
we eat our body shifts blood flow to a
digestive tract in part by releasing
noradrenaline to pull in blood from our
limbs this has been called The
gastrovascular Reflex so drinking water
was thought to be just a zero calorie
way of stretching our stomach but
instead drink two cups of saline
basically salt water and the metabolic
boost vanishes so stomach expansion can
explain the water effect we now realize
our body appears to detect osmolarity
the concentration of stuff within a
liquid covertly slip liquids of
different concentrations into people's
stomachs with a feeding tube and you can
demonstrate this by monitoring sweat
production which is kind of a proxy for
noradrenaline release um this may be a
spinal reflex as preserved in
quadriplegic or or picked up by the
liver as we see less noradrenaline
release and in liver transplant patients
who've had their liver nerve severed
whichever the pathway our body can tell
thought we only had five senses the
current count is upwards of 33 so maybe
the Bruce Willis movie should have been
called the 34th sense in my daily
doesn't recommendation I rank certain
teas as among the healthiest beverages
after all they have all the water of
water with an antioxidant bonus but from
a weight loss perspective plain water
may have an edge that may explain the
study showing overweight and obese
individuals randomized to replace diet
beverages with water lost significantly
more weight this was chocked up to
getting rid of all those artificial
sweeteners but maybe instead the diet
drinks were too concentrated to offer
the same water-induced metabolic boost
diet soda tea has about 10 times the
concentration of dissolved substances
compared to tap water so plain water on
an empty stomach may be the best does
the temperature of the water matter in a
journal published by the American
Society of mechanical engineers an
engineering Professor proposed that the
secret of a raw food diet for weight
loss was the temperature at which the
food was served to bring two cups of
even just room temperature water up to
body temperature he calculate the body
would have to dip into its fat stores
and use up
6,000 calories look just do the math
right he says uh calories defined as the
amount of energy required to raise one
gram of water one degre Celsius so since
two cups of water is about 500 gram and
the difference between room temp and
Body temp is about a dozen degrees C 500
* 12 equals 6,000 plus calories
needed anyone see the
mistake in Nutrition a calorie is
actually a kilo calor a thousand times
bigger than the same word used in the
rest of the Sciences confusing right
still I'm shocked the paper was even
published so drinking two cups of room
temperature water actually only takes
six calories to warm up not 6,000 now if
you were a hummingbird drinking four
times your body weight and chilly nectar
you could burn up to 2% of your energy
reserves warming it up but doesn't make
as much of a difference for us what
about really cold water though a letter
called the ice diet was published in the
anals of internal medicine estimated
that eating about a quart of ice like a
like a really really big snow cone with
no syrup could Rob our body of more than
150 calories the same amount of energy
as the calorie expenditure in running
one mile it's not like you directly burn
fat to warm up the water though I mean
what your body does is just crls more of
the waste heat you normally give off by
constricting blood flow to your skin how
does it do that nor adrenaline if you
compare drinking body temperature water
to room temperature water to cold water
there's only a significant constriction
in blood flow to the skin after the room
temp in cold water and neither the warm
or tempid water could boost metabolic
rate as much as cold fridge temperature
water so your body does after all end up
at least indirectly burning off more
calories when you drink your water cold
so two cups of cold water on an empty
stomach a few times a day does it matter
when yes watch my evidence-based weight
loss lecture to see how you can add the
benefit of negative calorie preloading
by drinking that water right before your
[Music]
meals